

SUMMARY

Highly ambitious IT business analyst with more than 10 years of experience into Retail Banking and BFSI domain. Worked in Waterfall and Agile methodology projects. Hands-on experience with Client interaction and understanding their business needs. An energetic, self-motivated team member with hands on experience in business analysis, requirements gathering, application integration, customization and team handling also analyzing processes and procedures and designing and implementing solutions.

SKILLS

- Client management.
- Team Handling.
- Requirement Gathering, requirement elicitation and requirement documentation.
- Prioritize requirement and create product backlog.
- Wireframes.
- Agile and Waterfall Methodologies, Agile Scrum.
- Workflow Diagrams.
- Gap Analysis.
- User Acceptance Testing and test case review.
- Interpersonal and communication skills.
- Business analysis and Business development.
- Retail Banking/BFSI and Insurance domain.
- BRD, FRD, Use case, User stories, Field Matrix.
- Strong analytical and organizational skills.
- API Integration.
- Software Development Life Cycle (SDLC).

AKHILESH TIWARI

LEAD BUSINESS ANALYST

WORK EXPERIENCE

Yes Bank Ltd. Lead Business Analyst.

12/2016 - 04/2024.

- Seasoned Business Analyst offering to Ten years of experience in Banking and BFSI Domain.
- Presented business process workflows to management and end user.
- Attended sprint planning meetings and work towards defining the sprint items along with the product stakeholders.
- Working knowledge of products like Banking and Insurance.
- Conduct day-to-day project coordination, planning, and implementation across multiple teams.
- Ensure issues are identified, tracked, reported on and resolved in a timely manner.
- Interacting with the technical team to ensure that the requirements are clear.
- Collaborated with cross-functional teams to implement operational improvements and business strategies.
- Organized and participated in all Agile practices.
- Handling changes requests, getting approval, impact analysis, maintaining CR log, follow-up with internal stakeholders ensuring delivery on time.
- Conducted Gap Analysis

ICICI Bank Ltd.

Sr. Business Analyst.

09/2014-09/2016.

- Experience in gathering requirements, proposing solutions until the requirements get freeze.
- Clear understanding of Software Development life cycle (SDLC) and process oriented. Experience in both agile and waterfall methodologies.
- Working knowledge of products like LMS.
- Documentation: BRD, FRD, Workflow Diagrams, Use Cases, Wireframes, User Stories.
- Requirement analysis- Gap analysis.
- Good knowledge of requirements elicitation, requirement documentation, use case definition.
- Performed test case reviews and demonstration, assisted UAT testing.

TOOLS

- Axure.
- JIRA.
- MS Visio.
- MS Office.
- Flex-Cube.

PROJECT

Yes Bank Ltd.

- Loan in Second (LIS).
- CASA System (Accounts).
- Escrow System (New Business).
- M Pro (Max Life).

ICICI Bank Ltd.

- Loan Management System.
- Customer Onboarding.

CERTIFICATIONS

- IRDA
- AMFI-VA

CONTACT

PHONE: 09713065999

EMAIL:

akhilesh.tiwari20@gmail.com

IIFL Finance.

Asst. Territory Manager

01/2013 - 09/2014.

- Conducted regular market assessments to stay current on trends and maintain readiness for changes.
- Established budgets for programmed activities and controlled expenditure to meet targets.
- Evaluated sales and service processes to generate targeted improvement strategies and increase revenue opportunities.
- Managed team of 30 staff, driving performance with motivational strategies to exceed sales targets.

IndusInd Bank.

Customer service manager

03/2011 - 12/2012

- Executed data-driven sales and marketing strategies to boost revenue.
- Planned staff roster to meet customer needs whilst remaining under budget.
- Organized continuous facilities cleaning, minimizing risk and maintaining professional appearance.
- Recruited customer service team members and mentored in company policies and best practices.

HSBC.

Assistant service manager.

11/2007 - 03/2011

- Prepared professional business correspondence on behalf of senior staff and organization.
- Assessed daily operational needs and requirements and used team meetings to encourage staff goal-achievement.
- Analyzed customer feedback and trends to drive process improvements.
- Resolved complex issues with strong analysis and investigations.

EDUCATION

SRK University M.A (Psychology) 78%.